Finding Aid for the Anna Ryder Dickey Collection Biomed.0213
UCLA Library Special Collections
Anna Ryder Dickey collection
1889-2000
UCLA Library Special Collections
Dickey, Anna Ryder
Biomed.0213
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection contains photographs (albums and separates), ephemera, and inscribed books documenting the friendship between Anna Ryder Dickey and celebrated naturalist and wilderness conservationist, John Muir. The albums document two Sierra Club nature trips that Muir, Mrs. Dickey, her adolescent son, Donald R. Dickey, and others took to Yosemite National Park, and Sequoia and King's Canyon National Parks, in 1896 and 1902 respectively. Of special note are six pictorialist style presentation photographs of John Muir alone or with Mrs. Dickey, taken by the Pasadena photographer Kraig. The book inscriptions, letters, and notes provide further proof of the Muir-Dickey friendship, while the books themselves, newspaper clippings, and magazine extracts highlight aspects of Muir's work, philosophy, and life story.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Donald R. Dickey, Jr. to the Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library, University of California, Los Angeles, January, 2001.
Mr. Dickey Jr.'s generous gift also included circa 180 glass "lantern" slides, hand-colored, of Californian, Canadian and Algerian land- and sea-scapes, people, firds, flowers and mammals. These had been taken by Donald R. Dickey Sr. and illustrated many of his public lectures. The slides are housed in the History and Special Collections Division with similar materials of Ms. Collection #59, the Donald Ryder Dickey Photographic Collection.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9953318403606533
Biography
ANNA RYDER DICKEY was born December 23, 1863 in Dubuque Iowa and died May 4, 1928 in Pasadena, California. She was the mother of Donald Ryder Dickey, Sr. and the grandmother of Donald Ryder Dickey, Jr. (from whom the collection was obtained). Prior to moving to Pasadena, she lived in Dubuque, marrying Ernest M. Dickey in 1885. The scrapbooks, photographs of John Muir, and related ephemera, were accumulated while residing in Pasadena (specifically, the area known as San Rafael Heights). As evidenced by the photographic material and several personal notes in the ephemera, she maintained a close friendship with Muir during this time.
DONALD RYDER DICKEY, Sr. (1887-1932), who is featured in several of the photographs in Scrapbook #2, was the son of Ernest and Anna Ryder Dickey. He was a respected innovator in and practitioner of wildlife photography and collector of Pacific Coast mammals and birds. In 1902, at age 16, he and his mother joined a Sierra Club group in travel up the King's River Cañon, eventually climbing and reaching the summit of Mount Whitney. The participants of this trip included John Muir, C. Hart Merriam, Dr. Henry Gannett, as well as historian Theodore Hittell and landscape artist William Keith.
During his senior year at Yale University, Dickey was stricken by a serious heart condition. Allowed to graduate because of his high academic standing, he returned to his parents' home in Pasadena for two years of rest. During this time he gradually returned to his former interest in the outdoors and began photographing and collecting birds and small mammals. Eventually he determined to establish a research center for vertebrate zoology in Southern California, with a study collection of specimens, with photographs and books to support it. The collection, which focused mainly on southwestern fauna of California and Mexico, but also included the birds of Laysan Island, and fauna of Michigan, New Brunswick, and Central America, was housed at the California Institute of Technology in the 1920s, and came to the University of California, Los Angeles after his death.
JOHN MUIR (1838-1914) was born in Dunbar, Scotland. In 1849 he and his family immigrated to Portage, Wisconsin. Muir was internationally renowned as a writer, naturalist and forest conservationist, particularly in his advocacy for the preservation of Yosemite Valley and adjacent wilderness areas of the Sierra Nevada's during the late 19th and early 20th centuries. He was also the first acting president of the Sierra Club from its founding in 1892 until his death. Through his publications and advocacy for environmental causes, Muir became one of the strongest figures in the early environmental and ecological movement within the United States.
Scope and Content
The collection documents the formal but close friendship that existed between Anna Ryder Dickey and John Muir in the last 20 years of his life, with two photo albums, separate photographs, letters, notes, and inscriptions. The numerous photographs also picture the looks of an earlier California and provide a little early history of the Sierra Club.
Housed separately with Ms. Collection #59, the Donald R. Dickey [Sr.] Photographic Collection, are 180 glass lantern slides of scenery and wildlife which were also part of Donald R. Dickey Jr.'s generous gift to UCLA.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Photographs, 1896-1910. 2 albums and 6 folders
Series 2. Ephemera, 1889-2000. 8 folders
Series 3. Books, 1901-1965. 10 volumes
Related Material
Donald Ryder Dickey photographic collection (Collection 59). Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections Division, University of California, Los Angeles.
Donald Ryder Dickey field notes (Manuscript collection 110). Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections Division, University of California, Los Angeles.
Donald R. Dickey personal photo album (Manuscript collection 301). Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, University of California, Los Angeles.
Donald Ryder Dickey personal papers (Manuscript collection 296). Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, University of California, Los Angeles.
Photograph albums; Zoologists -- United States -- Archives; Nature photography -- California; Natural history -- California -- Pictorial Works; Dickey, Donald R. (Donald Ryder); Muir, John
- Photographs, 1896-1910; Series 1.; 2 albums
  Scope and Contents note
  2 photo albums documenting Sierra Club trips in 1896 and 1902, and 6 loose photographs of John Muir and Anna Ryder Dickey, ca. 1910.
  - Photo Album 1, 1896; Subseries 1.; 1 boxed photo album, 30.5 x 25.5 cm
    Softcover album consisting of 16 leaves, with 98 black and white photographs mounted on 30 pages. It documents an early Sierra Club trip to Sequoia and Kings Canyon National Parks (Kings Canyon known at that time as General Grant National Park) and Yosemite National Park (Yosemite Valley). The photographs on each page are identified and described from: a) original notations written directly in the album; b) a handwritten partial list of photographs which was found inside the album; c) added descriptive text, indicated by brackets [ ]; pagination has also been added.
    - Page 1: Front cover. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      the word "Photographs" in upper left-hand corner
    - Page 2. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Three photographs: a) Giant Forest [Sequoia National Park]; b) Celeb'y Row: Bunnell, Lemmon, Keeler, Gannett, Merriam, Hittell, Keith, Muir; c) King's River.
    - Page 3. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Four photographs: a) Roaring River; b) Giant Forest; c) Bubb's Creek; d) leaving the Stage [men and women seated in or standing before a horse-drawn omnibus; camping equipment piled in a large mound].
    - Page 4. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Three photographs: a) Carry'g dunnage [back view of woman carrying 3 duffel bags]; b) Miss Bell's Tea [large group of men and women in a forest clearing]; c) Colby Rock [three women and one man resting on a large rock overlooking calm water, with a forest behind them].
    - Page 5. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Three photographs: a) King's River; b) Bullfrog Lake; c) four women just rising from their sleeping bags].
    - Page 6. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Four photographs: a) Mts. Brewer and University [mountain peaks and valley partially covered with snow]; b) breaking camp [four women and three men with packed duffel bags ready to depart]; c) Mrs. Sears. [mounted on a horse, holding a packed duffel bag on the horse's neck]; d) Camp Colby [group of people in a wooded camp site, with strung paper lanterns and an American flag in view].
    - Page 7. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Two photographs: a) above Bullfrog Lake [still lake with mountain peaks in the background]; b) loaded for bar [woman standing in wooded area aiming a rifle].
    - Page 8. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Two photographs: a) Com. Dep't [outdoor kitchen area with two Asian workers at their post looking at the camera]; b) grub time [outdoor eating area with people lined up to receive food].
    - Page 9. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Four photographs: a) Paradise Valley [mountain peak, with waterfall in foreground]; b) Mist Falls; c) Giant Forest [four women and one man standing on giant felled tree]; d) Great Boulder K.R.C. [man standing in front of giant boulder].
    - Page 10. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Three photographs: a) Bullfrog Lake; b) after lunch [group resting at a campsite; several people are holding fishing poles]; c) our camp [view of five women at campsite, with raised tent in background].
    - Page 11. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Five photographs: a) East Vidette [view of mountain peak, with a group of people on horseback in the foreground]; b) Roaring River [includes a youth ready to immerse a fishing net into the water]; c) Bullfrog Lake; d) Com. Dep't. [outdoor kitchen area ]; e) Giant Forest [man and woman standing at the base of a large Sequoia tree].
    - Page 12. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Two photographs: a) a human geyser [back view of a woman with long wavy hair which almost touches the ground, in a heavily forested area]; b) King's River].
    - Page 13. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Two photographs: a) Bubb's Creek]; b) Roaring River [also written and then crossed out: Copyright 1902 By Helen Leukens Jones].
    - Page 14. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Five photographs: a) Mist Falls; b) sequoia [four unidentified people posing at the base of a massive Sequoia tree]; c) Woodside [six unidentified people resting at a makeshift campsite]; d) lunch [view of seven people having lunch at a campsite; hanging paper lanterns and raised American flag in view]; e) King's River.
    - Page 15. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Three photographs: a) ant hill [man standing behind an ant hill]; b) coffee stand [view of campers taking an outdoor coffee break]; c) King's River.
    - Page 16. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Three photographs: a) Com. Dep't. [blurry photo of campsite commissary]; b) The Original 10 [group of men and women standing or sitting in an unidentified meadow]; c) mountains and clouds [photograph not identified, but may be an area below Mist Falls in Kings Canyon National Park].
    - Page 17. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Three photographs: a) Paradise Valley; b) Com. Dept. [outdoor kitchen and commissary, a group of campers taking refreshment; raised American flag in view]; c) Mist Falls.
    - Page 18. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Three photographs: a) M. on Cricket [woman, probably Anna Ryder Dickey, mounted]; b) King's River; c) Mist Falls.
    - Page 19. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Three photographs: a) King's River; b) Com. Dept. [outdoor commissary showing a raised tent and accompanying table under trees]; c) ready to start [a group of 19-20 men and women, mostly standing, a few on horseback].
    - Page 20. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Three photographs: a) University Peak; b) Mist Falls; c) Roaring River.
    - Page 21. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Three photographs: a) [Roaring River in King's River Cañon]; b) The Sphinx [mountain peak from King's River Canyon]; c) John Muir [reclining on the ground in the sun, King's River Cañon].
    - Page 22. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Four unidentified photographs: a) [two people in a small boat, possibly Anna Ryder Dickey and Donald R. Dickey, on Independence Lake]; b) [Independence Cottage]; c) [Hether Lake]; d) [Morgan Adams and Donald R. Dickey at Pinpond's (?)].
    - Page 23. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Three photographs, two unidentified: a) [junipers on Mt. Tallac]; b) [Tahoe from T(?) Wharf]; c) Independence Lake.
    - Page 24. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Three photographs [two unidentified]: a) [Independence Lake]; b) [Independence Lake]; c) Morgan Adams and D. [Donald R. Dickey, on Lake Tahoe shoreline].
    - Page 25. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Four unidentified photographs: a) [North Dome and Half Dome viewed from Yosemite Valley floor]; b) [sequoias in Giant Forest]; c) [on trip to Des. Valley]; d) [Yosemite Falls].
    - Page 26. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Four unidentified photographs: a) [Yosemite Falls as seen from Glacier Point]; b) [Mirror (Independence ?) Lake]; c) [Mirror (Independence ?) Lake]; d) [Cathedral Rocks].
    - Page 27. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Four unidentified photographs, probably all in Yosemite National Park: a) [Independence (?) Lake]; b) [Half Dome]; c) [Yosemite Falls]; d) [roots and trunk of a fallen giant sequoia, dwarfing a horse-drawn stagecoach].
    - Page 28. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Four unidentified photographs: a) [Bridalveil Falls ]; b) [Herb Lathrop and Harry Bissell on Glacier Point]; c) [Yosemite Valley showing El Capitan and Half Dome in background]; d) [Tehipite Dome(?), Kings Canyon National Park].
    - Page 29. (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Four unidentified photographs: a) [Vernal Falls]; b) [Liberty Cap and Nevada Falls]; c) [Leidig Meadow, Yosemite Valley]; d) [a man standing on Glacier Point looking out over Yosemite Valley].
    - Page 30. (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Five unidentified photographs: a) [Mirror Lake, with partial view of Mount Watkins)]; b) [Herb Lathorp on Glacier Point, Half Dome in background]; c) [view of both Upper and Lower Yosemite Falls]; d) [Mirror Lake]; e) [Vernal Falls].
  - Photo Album 2, 1902; Subseries 2.; 1 boxed album, 30.5 x 25.5 cm
    Softcover album consisting of 17 leaves, with 46 black and white photographs mounted on 19 pages. It documents an early Sierra Club horseback trip to Sequoia and Kings Canyon National Parks (Kings Canyon then known as General Grant National Park), with a side trip to the summit of Mt. Whitney. The participants were identified in an "Sierra Club Bulletin" article, May 1947, p. 86, as: John Muir, C. Hart Merriam, Henry Gannett, Theodore H. Hittell, William Kieth, Anna Ryder Dickey, Donald R. Dickey, Marian O. Hooker, Alicia Mosgrove, Helen Green, and "two Kinnie boys". Identification and description of the photographs come from the notations written directly in the album, with additional text or comments indicated by brackets [ ]. The page numbers have been added.
    - Page 1. Front cover. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      [Cover photo: travel party of men and women, 10 on horseback, 2 in automobile].
    - Page 2. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Mr. Muir [John Muir sitting on rock, taken at Mirror Lake, Yosemite National Park].
      handwritten and then crossed out on bottom left-hand corner of the photograph: "Copyright 1902 By Helen Leukens Jones".
    - Page 3. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Four photographs: a) Kaweah Peak [from Bear Paw]; b) Kern Cañon [evening]; c) [Upper] Bear Paw Meadows; d) Kern River.
    - Page 4. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Three photographs: a) Gen. Sherman [giant sequoias]; b) Upper Kern [Kern head waters]; c) Kaweah Peaks [from Alta Meadows].
    - Page 5. (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Three photographs: a) Kern-Kaweah [peaks with body of water in forefront]; b) Muir, Hittell, and Hopping [sitting on felled tree trunk]; c) [Crabtree Meadows and] Mt. Whitney.
    - Page 6. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Three photographs: a) Kern River [above Junction Meadow]; b) view from Bear Paw; c) Giant Forest [man and woman standing in front of a giant sequoia tree].
    - Page 7. (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Three photographs: a) Giant Forest [sequoia grove]; b) Kern R.; c) [Ellie Mosgrove on] Buttons.
    - Page 8. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Four photographs, identification on some illegible: a) Farewell Gap; b) Kern River; c) Kern River [above Junction Meadows]; d) Patsy and [Gray Rolk (?) trio and Miss Bunnell].
    - Page 9. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Three photographs: a) Upper Kern; b) [William] Keith, [Theodore] Hittell; c) Kern Cañon.
    - Page 10. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Three photographs: a) Kern Cañon [from top of descent to Cold Soda Spring]; b) on summit of Whitney [nine people, three identified as: D.R.D. (Donald R. Dickey), A.R.D. (Anna Ryder Dickey) and Muir; the others are Marian Hooker (grand-niece of Professor Josiah D. Whitney), Alicia Mosgrove, Henry Gannett, Theodore H. Hittell, Helen Green, and an unidentified youth]; c) Mt. Whitney [from Crabtree Meadows].
    - Page 11. (Box 2, Folder 11)
      One photograph: [view of unidentified valley with mountain peaks in background].
    - Page 12. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Two photographs: a) [view of meadows with mountain peaks in background]; b) [is same view as page 14, identified as "Kern-Kaweahs from Bear"].
    - Page 13. (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Two photographs: a) [Judge Hittell]; b) [floor of Kern].
    - Page 14. (Box 2, Folder 14)
      One photograph: Kern-Kaweahs from Bear [mountain peaks with possible reference to Bearpaw Meadow].
    - Page 15. (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Two photographs: a) [Kern-Kaweahs from Bear Paw]; b) [unidentified view of mountain range]
    - Page 16. (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Three photographs: a) [Kern view]; b) [mountain meadow flowers]; c) [Kern floor].
    - Page 17. (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Three photographs: a) [columnar basalt]; b) [natural bridge on Whitney (Voleans ? Creek)]; c) [erosion with creek].
    - Page 18. (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Three photographs: a) [Mohave Desert, with pack mules and mounted men]; b) [Mohave Desert, with pack mules and mounted men]; c) [unidentified waterfall].
    - Page 19. (Box 2, Folder 19)
      One photograph: [Mt. Shasta].
  - Separate Photographs, 1910; Subseries 3.; 6 folders
    Six photographs of John Muir and Anna Ryder Dickey, taken in California circa 1910. Each one has been signed by the photographer known as "Kraig." Approximately 6 x 4.5 inches, the photographs are each mounted on brown or gray paper, 9 x 12 inches.
    - John Muir., Warm-toned gelatin silver print (possibly a platinum print), 6 x 4.5 ". (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Portrait, full figure, standing in a meadow.
      verso of presentation mount is inscribed "Mr. John Muir"
    - Mother Dickey and John Muir., Gold-toned silver print, 6.5 x 4.5 ". (Box 3, Folder 2)
      John Muir and Anna Ryder Dickey standing in a landscaped garden.
      verso of presentation mount is inscribed "Mother Dickey and John Muir"
    - John Muir., Warm-toned (possibly platinum) print, 6 x 4.5 ". (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Side view of Muir seated in a garden.
      a rubber stamp on verso of brown paper mount: "BRYAN-BRANDENBURG CO./ Engravers Electrotypers/ Order No. 29677/ Date rec'd Jan 28 1925/ 232-36 East 4th St., Los Angeles, Calif; also on verso, two penciled handwritten printer's notes
    - Mother Dickey and John Muir., Platinum print, 6.25 x 4.25 ". (Box 3, Folder 4)
      John Muir and Anna Ryder Dickey, full figure, standing in a meadow.
      verso of brown paper mount is inscribed: "Mother Dickey and John Muir, San Rafael Heights, Pasadena"
    - Mother Dickey & John Muir., Gelatin silver print, 6.5 x 4.5 ". (Box 3, Folder 5)
      another print of the same negative as Box 4, Folder 4
    - Mother Dickey and John Muir., Gelatin silver print, 6.5 x 4.5 ". (Box 3, Folder 6)
      John Muir seated in a high-back wing chair with Mrs. Dickey looking over his shoulder.
      verso of grey paper mount is inscribed: "Mother Dickey and John Muir"
- Ephemera, 1889-2000; Series 2.; 8 folders
  Focus is on John Muir and his pursuits as a naturalist. Items consist mainly of newspaper and magazine articles and personal handwritten letters and notes. Also included are a Sierra Club brochure, one printed poem (on Muir), and a pocket calendar for the year 1889.
  - Dickey (Anna Ryder) Collection (Box 1, Folder 1)
    handwritten list identifying photos on pp. 21-30 of Photo Album 1.
    list is housed in Box 1 with the album
  - Ephemera found in Photo Album 2. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    handwritten list identifying photos on pp. 3-10 of Photo Album 2.
    list is housed in Box 2 with the album
  - Ephemera found in: "The mountains of California", by John Muir, 1901. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    handwritten list identifying photos on pp. 13-19 of Photo Album 2.
  - Ephemera found in Photo Album 2. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    a) three scraps of handwritten letters, with pen and ink sketches; b) one-paragraph clipping from unidentified newspaper, quoting John Muir; c) quarter-fold pocket calendar for the year 1889.
  - Ephemera found in: "Letters to a friend, written to Mrs. Ezra S. Carr, 1866-1879", by John Muir, 1915. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    a) letter from George Wharton James, Jan. 20, 1915 [clearly to Anna R. Dickey], requesting use of photos of Muir; b) newspaper clippings about John Muir, mostly obituaries.
  - Ephemera found in: "The life and letters of John Muir", by William Frederic Badè, 1924. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Newspaper clippings and articles about John Muir.
  - Ephemera found in: "John Muir and the Sierra Club; the battle for Yosemite", by Holway R. Jones, 1965. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    a) newspaper clipping about John Muir; b) Sierra Club brochure, undated; c) bookmark from Tillman Place Bookshop, San Francisco.
  - Ephemera found in: "The story of my boyhood and youth", by John Muir, 1913. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    a) newspaper clipping about John Muir; b) advertisement for book "The spell of the Rockies", by Enos A. Mills, 1911.
  - Ephemera found in: "Our national parks", by John Muir, 1902., 1903-1925 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    a) penciled note from John Muir to Anna Ryder Dickey, dated Dec. 9, 1911, from Montevideo, Uruguay; b) newspaper clipping, "Hombres de ciencia: El Doctor John Muir", identified in pencil as from "La Tribuna Popular", Dec. 7, 1911; c) book review by Louise Morgrage of "The life and letters of John Muir", by William Frederic Badè; page 11 torn from "California Southland" [no date; the magazine was published under this title from 1918 to 1929]; d) newspapers clippings about John Muir, one referring to the Hetch Hetchy water project; e) printed poem [source unidentified] by Bailey Millard: "Muir of the Mountains".
  - Ephemera found in: "Son of the wilderness; the life of John Muir", by Linnie Marsh Wolfe, 1945., 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Newspaper clipping: "A fresh look for Sierra Club".
  - Ephemera., 1932, 1934, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Magazine articles: a) "For the birds: a great reason to go to Midway...", by Maria Streshinsky, in: "VIA", May/Jun 2000, pp. 46-47; b) obituary of Donald Ryder Dickey, in: "The Auk", 49(4): 517-518, Oct 1932; c) "An appreciation of Donald Ryder Dickey", by Harry Harris, in: "The Condor", 36(2): 59-66, Mar/Apr 1934.
- Books, 1901-1965; Series 3.
  Ten books written by or about John Muir; several are autograph copies. The volumes have been cataloged and are shelved in the UCLA Biomedical Library History and Special Collections Rare Book Collection.
  - "The mountains of California", by John Muir. New York: Century Co., 1901, [c1894]. (Folder 1)
    Author's autograph presentation copy, inscribed on upper free endpaper to Anna R. Dickey, October 1902.
    Call Number: Biomed QH 105 C2 M898m 1901 Rare